<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Garnix on Gabriel Volpe</title><link>https://gvolpe.com/tags/garnix/</link><description>Recent content in Garnix on Gabriel Volpe</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 23:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gvolpe.com/tags/garnix/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>NixOS server up in minutes!</title><link>https://gvolpe.com/blog/nixos-server/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gvolpe.com/blog/nixos-server/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The folks at &lt;a href="https://garnix.io"&gt;Garnix&lt;/a&gt; have done it again! You can now deploy a &lt;a href="https://nixos.org/"&gt;NixOS server&lt;/a&gt; in minutes, just by defining your system on a &lt;code&gt;flake.nix&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;&amp;lsquo;ing your changes (Garnix needs to be enabled for the repo).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their latest blog post &lt;a href="https://garnix.io/blog/hosting-nixos"&gt;Hands-on NixOS servers&lt;/a&gt;, they explain all the necessary steps to deploy your own server, so I won&amp;rsquo;t repeat things over. Furthermore, there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://garnix.io/docs/hosting"&gt;official documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I will explain how I used this opportunity to set up a web analytics server for this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Private Nix flake 🔒</title><link>https://gvolpe.com/blog/private-flake/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gvolpe.com/blog/private-flake/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I blogged about &lt;a href="../garnix"&gt;Garnix&lt;/a&gt; before, and it&amp;rsquo;s the solution I&amp;rsquo;ve been using ever since for continuous integration. However, one thing I was missing was that private flakes were unsupported, so I had to live with a private local flake that I was commenting out on my public flake for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Github Actions does support building private flakes by providing an access token, but it&amp;rsquo;s not very secure if your builds end up on a public cache anyway (not my case, though)&amp;hellip; Garnix recently added &lt;a href="https://garnix.io/docs/private_inputs"&gt;support for private inputs&lt;/a&gt;, but it comes with some limitations (mainly due to security), so I could not take advantage of this new feature.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nix remote builds</title><link>https://gvolpe.com/blog/nix-remote-builds/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gvolpe.com/blog/nix-remote-builds/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Remote builds enable interesting use cases and experiments. Besides building for different architectures, another use case that comes to mind would be having a low-resource machine building a derivation that would require heavy CPU usage (e.g. a Rust application) on the fly, without having to rely on CI builds or binary caches, effectively used as a development environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what the &lt;a href="https://nixos.org/manual/nix/stable/advanced-topics/distributed-builds.html"&gt;NixOS official documentation&lt;/a&gt; has to say on the topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
.quote::before {
 content: var(--quote-emoji);
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class="quote" style="--quote-emoji: '📜';"&gt;
 &lt;h4&gt;Remote Builds&lt;/h4&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
"Nix supports remote builds, where a local Nix installation can forward Nix builds to other machines. This allows multiple builds to be performed in parallel and allows Nix to perform multi-platform builds in a semi-transparent way. For instance, if you perform a build for a &lt;code&gt;86_64-darwin&lt;/code&gt; on an &lt;code&gt;i686-linux&lt;/code&gt; machine, Nix can automatically forward the build to a &lt;code&gt;x86_64-darwin&lt;/code&gt; machine, if available."
&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Garnix CI</title><link>https://gvolpe.com/blog/garnix/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 21:45:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gvolpe.com/blog/garnix/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://garnix.io/"&gt;Garnix&lt;/a&gt; is a continuous integration (CI) service for Nix flakes that has been in Beta for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
.quote::before {
 content: var(--quote-emoji);
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class="quote" style="--quote-emoji: '📜';"&gt;
 &lt;h4&gt;In their own words&lt;/h4&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;
"With Nix-specific optimizations, Garnix makes CI with Nix fast — a few seconds for no-op changes. Easy to setup, too — if you have a flake.nix, you are ready to go. And we provide the build results as a cache, so you don't have to build things locally. To top it all up, we run on 100% renewable energy. Because CI should bring you peace of mind."
Notice the extensions we had to enable to make this compile.
&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>