<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cloud on Gabriel Volpe</title><link>https://gvolpe.com/tags/cloud/</link><description>Recent content in Cloud on Gabriel Volpe</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gvolpe.com/tags/cloud/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Immich Photos on S3 object storage</title><link>https://gvolpe.com/blog/immich-photos/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gvolpe.com/blog/immich-photos/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As someone who loves going for adventures abroad, the &lt;a href="https://gvolpe.com/classy-lens"&gt;memories&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve captured behind the lens have become extremely valuable to me. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to appreciate that I can still cherish those memories many years later, regardless of whether the source was a DSLR, a smartphone, or a GoPro. The feelings these precious memories rekindle are priceless; as a tech person, it&amp;rsquo;s only reasonable to seek out a &amp;lsquo;safe haven&amp;rsquo; for them.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Unison: Forex API &amp; Caching</title><link>https://gvolpe.com/blog/unison-forex/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gvolpe.com/blog/unison-forex/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I have been following the &lt;a href="https://www.unison-lang.org/"&gt;Unison programming language&lt;/a&gt; for as long as I can remember, given that &lt;a href="https://www.unison-lang.org/unison-computing/"&gt;its authors&lt;/a&gt; are very well-known in the Scala ecosystem. Though, it took me a good few years to finally learn it by immersing myself into their amazing documentation and tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR: I love it more and more every single day!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language itself is easy to learn for anyone coming from a functional programming background. Even their implementation of &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1611.09259"&gt;algebraic effects&lt;/a&gt; &amp;mdash; called &lt;a href="https://www.unison-lang.org/docs/fundamentals/abilities/"&gt;abilities&lt;/a&gt; &amp;mdash; are quite straightforward. What sets the language apart from others is their interactive approach to writing code.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>